Fetching one paper...

PMID: 42332970

<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="In-Process" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">42332970</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2026</Year><Month>06</Month><Day>23</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1463-5224</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>29</Volume><Issue>4</Issue><PubDate><Year>2026</Year><Month>Jul</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Veterinary ophthalmology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Vet Ophthalmol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Utility of Autologous Fascia Lata Grafting in Veterinary Ophthalmology: A Case Series of 5 Dogs.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e70217</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e70217</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/vop.70217</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">To describe the surgical technique and clinical outcomes associated with autologous fascia lata (AFL) grafting for the management of globe-threatening ophthalmic conditions in dogs.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Medical records of five canine patients undergoing ophthalmic surgery with AFL grafting between November 2024 and November 2025 were retrospectively reviewed. Indications included recurrent scleral staphyloma following failure of multi-layer porcine small intestinal submucosa grafting, conjunctival thinning overlying glaucoma drainage device tubing, and reconstruction following deep lamellar keratectomy and sclerectomy for limbal melanocytic tumors. Data collected included signalment, indication for surgery, surgical technique, post-operative management, donor site morbidity, and short- and long-term outcomes.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Minimally invasive AFL grafting was successfully used in all five cases to address globe-threatening ophthalmic conditions. In the two dogs treated for recurrent scleral staphyloma, the graft provided sustained tectonic support with no staphyloma recurrence at the last follow-up examinations performed six and 13&#x2009;months post-operatively. In the case involving conjunctival thinning over a glaucoma drainage device, conjunctival integrity was maintained without recurrence of erosion at the final follow-up at six months. In both cases of limbal melanocytic tumor resection, the graft provided adequate scleral reinforcement with preservation of globe integrity at the last follow-up examination at ten weeks and five months post-operatively. Donor site morbidity was minimal in all cases.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">AFL grafting provided reliable tectonic support and favorable biocompatibility in dogs undergoing ophthalmic surgery for globe-threatening defects.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>&#xa9; 2026 American College of Veterinary Ophthalmologists.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bell</LastName><ForeName>Magnolia</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0001-7525-705X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Perth Animal Eye Hospital, Perth, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dutton</LastName><ForeName>Anita</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Perth Animal Eye Hospital, Perth, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>King</LastName><ForeName>Martyn</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Perth Animal Eye Hospital, Perth, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Vet Ophthalmol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>100887377</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1463-5216</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">autologous grafting</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">glaucoma valve</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">limbal melanocytoma</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">scleral reconstruction</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">scleral staphyloma</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">sclerectomy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">tensor fascia lata</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2026</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>35</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2026</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>35</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2026</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2026</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2026</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2026</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>2</Hour><Minute>54</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">42332970</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/vop.70217</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>D.&#x2010;E. Lee, K.&#x2010;C. Kim, S.&#x2010;W. Jeong, and H. Y. Yoon, &#x201c;Reconstruction of Urethral Defects Using a Fascia Lata Autograft in a Dog,&#x201d; Journal of Veterinary Medical Science 81 (2019): 237&#x2013;240.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. N. Aron, B. A. Selcer, and J. D. Smith, &#x201c;Autogenous Tensor Fascia Lata Graft Replacement of the Patellar Ligament in a Dog,&#x201d; Veterinary and Comparative Orthopaedics and Traumatology 10 (1997): 141&#x2013;145.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. J. Gemmill and S. Carmichael, &#x201c;Complete Patellar Ligament Replacement Using a Fascia Lata Autograft in a Dog,&#x201d; Journal of Small Animal Practice 44 (2003): 456&#x2013;459.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Shani and R. Shahar, &#x201c;Repair of Chronic Complete Traumatic Rupture of the Common Calcaneal Tendon in a Dog, Using a Fascia Lata Graft: Case Report and Literature Review,&#x201d; Veterinary and Comparative Orthopaedics and Traumatology 13 (2000): 104&#x2013;108.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. A. Grundon, C. Hardman, A. O'Reilly, et&#xa0;al., &#x201c;Repair of a Scleral Defect With an Autogenous Fascia Lata Graft in a Dog,&#x201d; Veterinary Ophthalmology 14 (2011): 271&#x2013;274.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Hoerdemann and T. Yarbrough, &#x201c;Long&#x2010;Term Outcome of Autologous Fascia Lata Grafting With Conjunctival Flap Overlay in Horses With Ulcerative Keratitis and Keratomalacia,&#x201d; Veterinary Surgery 52 (2023): 1032&#x2013;1040.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Bongartz, F. Carofiglio, M. Balligand, M. Heimann, and A. Hamaide, &#x201c;Use of Autogenous Fascia Lata Graft for Perineal Herniorrhaphy in Dogs,&#x201d; Veterinary Surgery 34 (2005): 405&#x2013;413.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Lores, P. Rakestraw, M. De Rijck, et&#xa0;al., &#x201c;Use of Autologous Fascia Lata Graft to Repair a Complex Corneal Ulcer in a Mare,&#x201d; Irish Veterinary Journal 73 (2020): 7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>B. J. Skorobohach and D. V. H. Hendrix, &#x201c;Staphyloma in a Cat,&#x201d; Veterinary Ophthalmology 6 (2003): 93&#x2013;97.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>B. Singh, Dyce, Sack, and Wensing's Textbook of Veterinary Anatomy, Fifth ed. (Elsevier, 2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. M. Tanji, D. C. Lundy, D. S. Minckler, D. K. Heuer, and R. Varma, &#x201c;Fascia Lata Patch Graft in Glaucoma Tube Surgery,&#x201d; Ophthalmology 103 (1996): 1309&#x2013;1312.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Kobtan, &#x201c;Use of Autologous Fascia Lata as a Natural Biomaterial for Tectonic Support in Surgically Induced Necrotizing Scleritis,&#x201d; Eye 29 (2015): 580&#x2013;584.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>N. Kalashnikov, J. Barralet, and J. Vorstenbosch, &#x201c;Implantable Medical Devices, Biomaterials, and the Foreign Body Response: A Surgical Perspective,&#x201d; Journal of Biomedical Materials Research. Part A 113 (2025): e37983.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>G. A. Lewin, &#x201c;Repair of a Full Thickness Corneoscleral Defect in a German Shepherd Dog Using Porcine Small Intestinal Submucosa,&#x201d; Journal of Small Animal Practice 40 (1999): 340&#x2013;342.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. A. Wilkie and E. D. Wolf, &#x201c;Treatment of Epibulbar Melanocytoma in a Dog, Using Full&#x2010;Thickness Eyewall Resection and Synthetic Graft,&#x201d; Journal of the American Veterinary Medical Association 198 (1991): 1019&#x2013;1022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. C. Norman, J. L. Urbanz, and S. T. Calvarese, &#x201c;Penetrating Keratoscleroplasty and Bimodal Grafting for Treatment of Limbal Melanocytoma in a Dog,&#x201d; Veterinary Ophthalmology 11 (2008): 340&#x2013;345.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. J. Featherstone, P. Renwick, C. L. Heinrich, and S. Manning, &#x201c;Efficacy of Lamellar Resection, Cryotherapy, and Adjunctive Grafting for the Treatment of Canine Limbal Melanoma,&#x201d; Veterinary Ophthalmology 12, no. Suppl 1 (2009): 65&#x2013;72.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. F. Sanchez, E. C. Ledbetter, and M. Leiva, &#x201c;Reconstruction of Deep and Perforating Corneal Defects in Dogs&#x2010;A Review (Part I/III): Autogenous Ocular Tissues, Donor Tissues, and Corneal Clarity Scoring,&#x201d; Veterinary Ophthalmology 28 (2025): 519&#x2013;531.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. M. Balaji, &#x201c;Efficacy of Autogenous Fascia Lata and Silicone Aurosling in Correction of Congenital Blepharoptosis by Frontalis Suspension,&#x201d; Indian Journal of Dental Research 29 (2018): 166&#x2013;170.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Gupta, S. Natarajan, S. Vaidya, et&#xa0;al., &#x201c;Traumatic Eye Ball Luxation: A Stepwise Approach to Globe Salvage,&#x201d; Saudi Journal of Ophthalmology 31 (2017): 260&#x2013;265.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Bussieres, S. G. Krohne, J. Stiles, and W. M. Townsend, &#x201c;The Use of Porcine Small Intestinal Submucosa for the Repair of Full&#x2010;Thickness Corneal Defects in Dogs, Cats and Horses,&#x201d; Veterinary Ophthalmology 7 (2004): 352&#x2013;359.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Luo and Z. Zhou, &#x201c;Application of Multi&#x2010;Layer Porcine Small Intestinal Submucosa for the Reconstruction of Deep Corneal Defects in Cats,&#x201d; Veterinary Ophthalmology 28 (2025): 264&#x2013;274.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. Barachetti, M. Zanni, D. Stefanello, and A. Rampazzo, &#x201c;Use of Four&#x2010;Layer Porcine Small Intestinal Submucosa Alone as a Scaffold for the Treatment of Deep Corneal Defects in Dogs and Cats: Preliminary Results,&#x201d; Veterinary Record 186 (2020): e28.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Jones, &#x201c;Repair of a Corneoscleral Staphyloma in a Cat Using Autologous Pinnal Cartilage in; Abstracts: Annual Scientific Meeting of the European College of Veterinary Ophthalmologists, Antwerp, Belgium May 23&#x2010;26, 2019,&#x201d; Veterinary Ophthalmology 22 (2019): e6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. Kanai, N. Kanemaki, S. Matsuo, Y. Ichikawa, H. Okujima, and Y. Wada, &#x201c;Excision of a Feline Limbal Melanoma and Use of Nictitans Cartilage to Repair the Resulting Corneoscleral Defect,&#x201d; Veterinary Ophthalmology 9 (2006): 255&#x2013;258.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. S. M. Barros and A. M. V. Safatle, &#x201c;Congenital Scleral Staphyloma in a Dog Repaired With Preserved Homologous Peritoneum,&#x201d; Veterinary Ophthalmology 3 (2000): 27&#x2013;29.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Barros, A. Safatle, T. Malerba, et&#xa0;al., &#x201c;The Surgical Repair of the Cornea of the Dog Using Pericardium as a Keratoprosthesis,&#x201d; Brazilian Journal of Veterinary Research and Animal Science 32 (1995): 251&#x2013;255.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Blogg, A. Dutton, and R. Stanley, &#x201c;Use of Third Eyelid Grafts to Repair Full Thickness Defects in the Cornea and Sclera,&#x201d; Journal of the American Animal Hospital Association 25 (1989): 505&#x2013;510.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. D. Westermeyer, D. V. H. Hendrix, and D. A. Ward, &#x201c;Long&#x2010;Term Evaluation of the Use of Ahmed Gonioimplants in Dogs With Primary Glaucoma: Nine Cases (2000&#x2010;2008),&#x201d; Journal of the American Veterinary Medical Association 238 (2011): 610&#x2013;617.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>W. C. Stewart, C. J. Kristoffersen, C. M. Demos, M. G. Fsadni, and J. A. Stewart, &#x201c;Incidence of Conjunctival Exposure Following Drainage Device Implantation in Patients With Glaucoma,&#x201d; European Journal of Ophthalmology 20 (2010): 124&#x2013;130.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Prinz, K. Mercieca, L.&#x2010;J. F&#xf6;rster, et&#xa0;al., &#x201c;Tube Erosions Following Glaucoma Drainage Device Implantations,&#x201d; Scientific Reports 15 (2025): 26056.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. Guerra Guimar&#xe3;es, K. Menezes Cardoso, P. Tralh&#xe3;o, et&#xa0;al., &#x201c;Current Therapeutics and Future Perspectives to Ocular Melanocytic Neoplasms in Dogs and Cats,&#x201d; Bioengineering 8 (2021): 225.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Donaldson, J. Sansom, T. Scase, V. Adams, and C. Mellersh, &#x201c;Canine Limbal Melanoma: 30 Cases (1992&#x2010;2004). Part 1. Signalment, Clinical and Histological Features and Pedigree Analysis,&#x201d; Veterinary Ophthalmology 9 (2006): 115&#x2013;119.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>V. Andreani, A. Guandalini, N. D'Anna, et&#xa0;al., &#x201c;The Combined Use of Surgical Debulking and Diode Laser Photocoagulation for Limbal Melanoma Treatment: A Retrospective Study of 21 Dogs,&#x201d; Veterinary Ophthalmology 20 (2017): 147&#x2013;154.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. L. Mathes, P. A. Moore, and A. E. Ellis, &#x201c;Penetrating Sclerokeratoplasty and Autologous Pinnal Cartilage and Conjunctival Grafting to Treat a Large Limbal Melanoma in a Dog,&#x201d; Veterinary Ophthalmology 18 (2015): 152&#x2013;159.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. M. &#xc5;hlberg, K. Salla, O. M. Laitinen&#x2010;Vapaavuori, and S. H. M&#xf6;ls&#xe4;, &#x201c;Treatment of Canine Perineal Hernia With a Fascia Lata Graft Is Noninferior to the Elevation of the Internal Obturator Muscle: A Prospective Randomized Trial of 66 Dogs,&#x201d; Journal of the American Veterinary Medical Association 262 (2024): 1&#x2013;9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. A. Dominguez, S. Viviano, and D. Wang, &#x201c;Muscle Hernia Repair at Fascia Lata Autograft Donor Site,&#x201d; Eplasty 25 (2025): e9.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>
